<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Brief conclusions of dancers and dancing Condemning the prophane vse thereof; and commending the excellencie of such persons which haue from age to age, in all solemne feasts, and victorious triumphs, vsed that (no lesse) honourable, commendable and laudable recreation: as also true physicall obseruations for the preseruation of the body in health, by the vse of the same exercise. Written by I.L. Roscio.</title>
            <title>Conclusions upon dances, both of this age, and of the olde</title>
            <author>Lowin, John, 1576-1659.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1609</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 24 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 12 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-04">2011-04 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A06404</idno>
            <idno type="STC">STC 16875</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC S106398</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99842115</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99842115</idno>
            <idno type="VID">6744</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A06404)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 6744)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 721:03)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>Brief conclusions of dancers and dancing Condemning the prophane vse thereof; and commending the excellencie of such persons which haue from age to age, in all solemne feasts, and victorious triumphs, vsed that (no lesse) honourable, commendable and laudable recreation: as also true physicall obseruations for the preseruation of the body in health, by the vse of the same exercise. Written by I.L. Roscio.</title>
                  <title>Conclusions upon dances, both of this age, and of the olde</title>
                  <author>Lowin, John, 1576-1659.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[24] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>For Iohn Orphinstrange, and are to bee sold at his shop by the Cocke and Katherine-wheel neere Holbourne bridge,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>Imprinted at London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1609.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>I.L. Roscio = John Lowin.</note>
                  <note>A reissue of "Conclusions upon dances, both of this age, and of the olde", STC 16874. The title page was printed by W. Hall on A1, originally blank; the original title page and dedication (A2-3) are cancelled in the only known copy.</note>
                  <note>Signatures: A⁴ (-A2,3) B-C⁴ D² .</note>
                  <note>Considerable print show-through.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the British Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Acting --  Religious aspects --  Christianity --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Dance --  Religious aspects --  Christianity --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Dance --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2009-12</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-12</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-02</date>
            <label>Kayla Ondracek</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-02</date>
            <label>Kayla Ondracek</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-04</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:6744:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:6744:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>Brief Concluſions of Dancers and Dancing.</p>
            <p>Condemning the prophane vſe thereof; <hi>and commending the excellencie of ſuch Perſons</hi> which haue from Age to Age, in all ſolemne <hi>Feaſts, and victorious Trumphs, vſed that</hi> (no leſſe) Honourable, Commendable and laudable Recreation:</p>
            <p>As alſo true Phyſicall obſeruations for the <hi>preſeruation of the body in health, by</hi> the vſe of the ſame Exerciſe. Written by <hi>I. L. Roſcio.</hi>
            </p>
            <figure>
               <head>SIC CREDE</head>
            </figure>
            <p>Imprinted at London, for <hi>Iohn Orphinstrange,</hi> and are to bee ſold at his ſhop by the <hi>Cocke</hi> and <hi>Katherine-wheele</hi> neere <hi>Holbourne bridge.</hi> 1609.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="to_the_reader">
            <pb facs="tcp:6744:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:6744:2"/>
            <head>THE PRINTER TO the Reader.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">L</seg>Et mee now entreate thee, courteous &amp; tractable Rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der, not to ſtay thy minde vpon the word, Dances: but to make thy recourſe thorow the matters, which are deduced vnder that title. For what cauſe? Otherwiſe the ſubiect of this purpoſe, as I thinke, ſhall ſeeme vnto thy iudgement, to be vaine and friuolous, whereas of it ſelfe, it is altogether ſerious, and of a great moment. Heare mee a little. The Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thor of this Treatiſe concerning Dances, doth not lay the foundation of his arguments vpon his owne opinion, nor vpon the fantaſticall imagi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nations of ſome others: but vpon the word of GOD it ſelfe, which is comprehended in the Holy Bookes of the Olde and Newe Teſtaments.
<pb facs="tcp:6744:3"/>The which thing may verie plainely be diſcerned, by the vnion, or congruitie of this ſmall Treatiſe, being not framed according to the pleaſure of the eye, but for the comfort of the heart: In which comfort theſe holy men and women (which he hath named, and before our eyes heere erected) magnified the moſt mightie Creator of all viſible and inuiſible crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures, holding it to bee their dutie, not onely pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uately to laud and reioyce in him for the victories they receiued: but alſo to ſtirre vp the people (which they ruled,) by the actiuenes and agilitie of their bodies in Dances, to praiſe and laud the immortall worker of their triumphs: Therefore bee thou inſtruc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted by the doctrine heerein contained: and the Lord haue thee alwaies vnder his protection.</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>Your friend <hi>IOHN ORPHINSTRANGE.</hi>
               </signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb facs="tcp:6744:3"/>
            <head>CONCLVSIONS VPON DANCES, BOTH OF THIS AGE AND OF THE OLD.</head>
            <head type="sub">Three diuers opinions of learned men, concer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning Dances.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">C</seg>Reat is the diuerſitie of opinions about the vſage of dances, euen as it is about a thouſand other matters of no ſlender im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>portance. Some men of good vnderſtanding and litterature, doe affirme dances to bee holy of themſelues: and their chiefe allegation regardeth the ſixt Chapter of the ſecond booke of <hi>Samuel,</hi> where it is writ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten, that the Prophet <hi>Dauid</hi> danced before the Arke of the Lord, when it was carried from the houſe of <hi>Obed-Edom</hi> to the Citie of <hi>Dauid,</hi> with ſhouting and ſound of Trumpet. Many others doe maintaine, that ſuch an exerciſe is pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phane: and doe principally inferre out of the
<pb facs="tcp:6744:4"/>32. chapter of <hi>Exodus,</hi> that the corrupted <hi>Iſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raelites</hi> did dance in their idolatrie about the molten Calfe, which they compelled <hi>Aaron</hi> to make. But after the iudgement of the grea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter number, it is a thing altogether indifferent: and their higheſt argument doth embrace one ſpeech of Chriſt in the 7. chap. of the Goſpell according to Saint <hi>Luke,</hi> which is this, <hi>They are like vnto little children ſitting in the mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ket place, and crying one to another, and ſay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, VVee haue piped vnto you, and ye haue not danced: wee haue mourned vnto you, and you haue not wept.</hi> Let the hearers and readers open their mindes vnto vs, or vnto others, vpon ſuch di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerſities.</p>
            <p>It may eaſily be perceiued, in marking ſome places of the Old and New Teſtaments, that the holineſſe, prophanation, and indifferencie of dances, muſt be conſidered vpon the cauſes of dancing. Wherefore wee are minded to ſet downe, by the permiſſion of the Almightie, ſome inſtructiue obſeruations touching that purpoſe.</p>
            <div type="part">
               <pb facs="tcp:6744:4"/>
               <head>Of the Dances vſed in the <hi>Old Age, and formerly of</hi> the holy.</head>
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>Hat Dance was holy, which, as wee read in the 15. chap. of <hi>Exodus,</hi> was effected by <hi>Miriam</hi> the Propheteſſe, ſiſter of <hi>Aa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ron</hi> and <hi>Moſes,</hi> with all the other <hi>Iſraelitiſh</hi> wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men, when God had mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raculouſly deſtroyed their deadly foes the <hi>Ae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gyptians,</hi> to wit, King <hi>Pharao</hi> and his mightie hoſte, in ouerthrowing and drowning them all at once in the red Sea. For they danced in ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ging prayſes vnto God for their deliuerance: and ſo the cauſe of their dancing was godly, and conſequently the dance it ſelfe was ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly. That Dance was holy likewiſe, which the Scripture ſheweth vs in the 11. chap. of <hi>Iudges,</hi> when <hi>Iptah</hi> had vanquiſhed his ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerſaries the <hi>Ammonites,</hi> and returned to his houſe: which <hi>Ammonites</hi> had beene verie cruel oppreſſors of the <hi>Iſraelits</hi> eighteen years.
<pb facs="tcp:6744:5"/>For the daughter of <hi>Iaphtah</hi> with her compa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>panions went out to meete her father, and dan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ced in magnifying the Lord, becauſe he had giuen him the victorie ouer his enemies.</p>
               <p>Is not the like argument to be framed vpon the like ſubiect, in the 18. chap. of the firſt book of <hi>Samuel?</hi> We ſee there, how that the women of <hi>Iſrael</hi> came out of all their Cities, to ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour <hi>Dauid</hi> returning from the ſlaughter of <hi>Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liath</hi> the Philiſtim: and how that they danced in giuing glorie to the Almightie, becauſe hee had auenged his people <hi>Iſrael</hi> of their foes the <hi>Philiſtims,</hi> which were ſlaundering and blaſpheming idolaters. And the 15. Chapter of the booke of <hi>Iudith</hi> doth confirme this mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter of dancing, in that it manifeſteth the <hi>Dan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces</hi> of that moſt vertuous, godly, and valiant widow <hi>Iudith,</hi> after ſhe had ſaued the Citie of <hi>Bethulia,</hi> and diſcomfited the <hi>Perſians, Medes,</hi> and all the reſt, by ſmiting off, with her heroi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>call hand, the head of <hi>Olofernes,</hi> chiefe Cap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine of <hi>Nabuchodonoſor</hi> King of the <hi>Aſſyrians.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <pb facs="tcp:6744:5"/>
               <head>Vpon what occaſions, in the <hi>Old Age, the dances were</hi> vſed.</head>
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">N</seg>Ow euerie man may learne by thoſe premiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes, that the godly wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men of <hi>Iſraell</hi> did dance publikly, after ſome great victorie, in prayſing and glorifying the name of the Lord for the ſame: and that they did not vſe that kinde of exerciſe with any minde toward ſome worldly pleaſure. But was it onely about victories? It was alſo a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bout the celebration of ſome ſolemne feaſt conſecrated vnto God: as we haue the example thereof in the 21. Chap. of <hi>Iudges.</hi> For the Elders of <hi>Iſrael</hi> hauing no wiues for two hun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dreth men of <hi>Beniamin</hi> had them goe to <hi>Shiloh,</hi> where a feaſt of the Lord was celebrated euery yeare: ſaying, Goe and lye in wait in the Vine<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>yards, and when ye ſee the daughters of <hi>Shiloh</hi> come out to dance in Dances, then come yee out of the Vineyardes, and catch you euery
<pb facs="tcp:6744:6"/>man a wife of the daughters of <hi>Shiloh,</hi> and goe into the land of <hi>Beniamin.</hi> So ye may clearely ſee, that the vſage of dancing was not onely or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dained for victories, but alſo for ſolemne feaſts: and that a concluſion may be gathered out of it, to be lawfull to reioyce with dances, at the time of mariages, and of all other holy and great occaſions. But it were meete and conuenient, ye ſhould alwaies remember one thing: that whenſoeuer the occaſions of dan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cing are holy, then the forme of dancing ought to repreſent holineſſe, as the indifferent doe require indifferencie: the diſcerning wher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of muſt be left to the iudgement of godly and well learned perſons.</p>
               <p>Wee doe not adde to this place the hiſtorie contained in the ſixt chap. of the ſecond booke of <hi>Samuel,</hi> which ſaith, That the Prophet <hi>Da<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uid</hi> danced before the Arke of God: becauſe a doubt may riſe thereupon, whether that mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of <hi>Dauid</hi> was a dance, or not. For as in the 82. <hi>Pſalme,</hi> and in other doctrines of the holy Bible, Princes and Magiſtrates are called Gods, becauſe in a manner they bee like vnto God: ſo that motion of <hi>Dauid</hi> might be taken in the number of dances, becauſe it had ſome likeneſſe with them. What is that, which com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pelleth
<pb facs="tcp:6744:6"/>vs to argue in this ſort? I pray you, hearken a little. Dances are motions com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſed with meaſure: but that motion of <hi>Dauid</hi> was without meaſure: as it is not difficult to be comprehended, in that he diſcouered himſelfe before his maids, whereupon hee was mocked of his wife <hi>Michal.</hi> What might haue beene the cauſe of ſuch a motion in him? His minde was tranſported and carried away, through the great vehemencie of the burning zeale, where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>with hee was altogither inflamed.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>Of the Vnlawfull Dances, <hi>which are commonly cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led</hi> prophane.</head>
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">A</seg>S touching prophane <hi>Dances,</hi> that <hi>Dance</hi> which the Apoſtle Saint <hi>Mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thew</hi> in the 14. Chapter of his Goſpell, writeth to haue beene danced before <hi>Herod</hi> by the daugh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter of <hi>Herodias,</hi> may be a ſufficient teſtimoniall. There it clearely appeareth to all perſons en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dued with ſome diſcretion, that in her Dance
<pb facs="tcp:6744:7"/>ſhe had no regard vnto God, but onely vnto <hi>Herod:</hi> that ſhe might moſt excellently pleaſe the ſaid <hi>Herod,</hi> to the intent that he ſhould make her ſome extraordinarie high promiſe, whereby ſhe might purchaſe to her ſelfe the head of Saint <hi>Iohn Baptiſt,</hi> for to carrie it to her mother <hi>Herodias,</hi> which did hate that good Prophet with a deadly hatred. And wee con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clude thereupon that euery dancer and dance<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reſſe, which in their dances haue no remem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brance of God, are greatly culpable before the eyes of God himſelfe, although they ſeeme to be without fault in the ſight of men.</p>
               <p>Wee do not bring hither the dancing men<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tioned in the 23. Chap. of <hi>Exodus:</hi> becauſe thoſe ſtubborn and ſtiffehearted <hi>Iſraelites,</hi> which dan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ced about the molten Calfe, were become I<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dolaters. For it might be in that conſideration, that ſuch dances were part of their religion.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <pb facs="tcp:6744:7"/>
               <head>Of ſuch Dances, as by reaſon are eſtemed to <hi>be indifferent.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">B</seg>Vt for the indifferencie of <hi>Dances,</hi> wee haue the 15. Chapter of the <hi>Euangeliſt S. Luke:</hi> where our Saui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>our <hi>Ieſus Chriſt</hi> ſpeaking of the Prodigall Sonne, which had waſted abroad all his portion of Goods, and afterward was returned to his Father, with humble confeſsion of his offence, ſayth in good part, &amp; in the narration of a godly deed, that they made great mirth for his ſake in the houſe, with Bankers, Melodie, and <hi>Dances.</hi> And there that indifferencie of <hi>Dancing,</hi> is to be more plainely ſeene in theſe wordes, <hi>Let vs eate, and be merrie.</hi> King <hi>Salomon</hi> among many indifferent thinges, which he ſetteth down for our inſtruction, in the 3. Chapter of his <hi>Eccleſiaſtes,</hi> doeth alſo teach vs this: <hi>That as there is a time to mourne, ſo there is a time to Dance.</hi> And ſuch a thing may alſo ſerue vs heere, for the proofe of the indifferencie of
<pb facs="tcp:6744:8"/>
                  <hi>Dances:</hi> concluding beſides that, by the laſt ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ample and doctrine now deduced, that it is not any action diſpleaſant vnto God, to vſe <hi>Dances</hi> for an honeſt recreation, in the ioyfull meetings of faythfull friendes, or deare kinsfolkes; and in all other occaſions like vnto that ſame.</p>
               <p>Wee do not vſe heere, that compariſon of the little Children, inuiting other little Children to <hi>Dance,</hi> comprehended in the 7. Chap. of the Goſpell according to <hi>S. Luke,</hi> which compari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon the Lord <hi>Ieſus</hi> vttered for himſelfe, and for the Prophet <hi>S. Iohn Baptiſt,</hi> againſt the <hi>Phariſes</hi> and Expounders of the Law. For it is well kno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wen euery where, that many thinges are to be tollerated in Children, which are not to be tol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lerated in other perſons: as the ryding vpon Stickes, and the playing with Babies; with ſuch other fooliſh paſtimes.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>What ſort of Dancing is more <hi>conuenient for the health.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">A</seg>Mong the indifferent <hi>Dances,</hi> thoſe <hi>Dances</hi> as we thinke, muſt be numbred, which are practiſed for the exerciſe of the body, that thereby the bodily health may be better preſerued. Wher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore
<pb facs="tcp:6744:8"/>in regarding the druerſitie of diſpoſitions, which is founde at all times in the humaine kinde, it will not bee amiſſe, to ſet downe one worde in this purpoſe, to declare what ſort of <hi>Dancing</hi> is more conuenient for theſe, and what for thoſe.</p>
               <p>Such <hi>Dances</hi> as doe ſtrongly ſtirre the body, ought to be choſen of them, which haue ſome obſtructions in the wayes of the Vrine, or ſome other like impediment. And the contrarie muſt be vſed of ſuch perſons, as doe perceiue their owne Braines to be weake, or the like infirmi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie to be in ſome other part. But to the others that Dancing is fitter, which exerciſeth the bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>die in a meane meaſure of agitation. Therefore let all thoſe perſons, which doe ordinarily exer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciſe them ſelues in <hi>Dances,</hi> carefully obſerue and regard the conſtitutions of their bodyes: to the intent, that they ſhould not vſe any kind of <hi>Dan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cing,</hi> which by repugnancie might be hurtfull to their complxions: Remembring aſsidually within them ſelues, and ſo much the more in this matter, to acknowledge God to be the Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thor of all good thinges: becauſe the Apoſtle <hi>S. Paul</hi> in the 4. Chap. of his firſt Epiſtle to <hi>Timo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>theus</hi> doth condemne the bodily exerciſe, when it is not accompanied with godlines.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <pb facs="tcp:6744:9"/>
               <head>Of the ordinarie Dances, vſed <hi>cuerie where, in theſe dayes.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">N</seg>Ow that we haue handled the <hi>Dances</hi> of the old Age, ſhall wee make euident in few lines, what wee thinke of the <hi>Dances</hi> of our dayes? Theſe <hi>Dances</hi> (I ſpeake of the greater part of them) doe ſeeme vnto our iudge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, to be partly vaine, and partly prophane. Vaine, becauſe neither men nor women are a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble to attaine vnto the knowledge and practiſe of the art of ſuch <hi>Dancing,</hi> without vexation of the Spirit, and loſſe of time. Prophane, becauſe in the old age, the women <hi>Danced</hi> to this intent, that thereby their ſpirituall Songes and Diuine prayſes ſhould waxe more feruent; and conſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quently become more acceptable vnto GOD: wheras now very often, in a great many places, among the Chriſtians them-ſelues, not onely the Women, but alſo the Men, doe <hi>Dance</hi> to pleaſe the world. Notwithſtanding God alone is hee, which ſeeth their heartes and intentions: and without difficultie it may be, that our con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iectures
<pb facs="tcp:6744:9"/>are not ſufficiently iudicious.</p>
               <p>The vexation of the Spirit is ſo much ſpoken againſt, by that wiſe <hi>Salomon</hi> in his Booke of <hi>Ecceſiaſtes,</hi> that it is a wonderfull thing, to ſee ſo many, &amp; ſo many againe, that neuer keepe them ſelues from the tearing clawes of that monſter. And the loſſe of Time, might be better auoy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded, if men would but note the admonition of the Apoſtle <hi>S. Paul,</hi> in the 5. Chap. of his Epiſtle to the <hi>Epheſians,</hi> where hee biddeth them <hi>Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deeme the time:</hi> when hee admoniſheth them, <hi>To walke circumſpectly, not as Fooles; but as Wiſe, and to vnderſtand what the will of the Lord is.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Moreouer, many of theſe <hi>Dances</hi> are ſo much artificiall (at the leaſt within our cogitations, and within the cogitations of ſome other perſons, which haue alſo obſerued in the holy Hiſtories of the old Teſtament, the manner of <hi>Dancing</hi> practiſed among the <hi>Iſraelitiſh</hi> women, that liued in the feare of God) many of theſe <hi>Dances</hi> (I ſay) are ſo much artificiall, that the humaine mindes can not be intended nor attentiue to the Art of <hi>Dancing,</hi> and to the prayſe of God together.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <pb facs="tcp:6744:10"/>
               <head>Whether it bee lawfull for men <hi>to dance with women.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">M</seg>Any men doe argue, that it is lawfull for them, to dance with women: be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe (ſay they) the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phet <hi>Dauid</hi> exhorteth vs in one of his <hi>Pſalmes,</hi> to praiſe God in <hi>Dances.</hi> But that argument cannot bee ſtrong enough. For beſides that the <hi>Hebrewe</hi> word doth carry diuers ſignifications, the later and riper Tranſlations, both in <hi>Engliſh</hi> and in other Languages, doe not name any <hi>Dance.</hi> Therefore we would rather counſell them to take an other way, and ſende them to that Text of the Prophet <hi>Ieremie</hi> in the 31. Chapter, <hi>The Virgine ſhall reioyce in the Dance, and the yong men and the olde men together: for I will turne their mourning into ioy, &amp; will comfort them, and giue them ioy for their ſorrowes.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Heere many others do endeuour themſelues, to make an oppoſition in this manner. As the flowing of milke and hony (ſay they) is taken in the Scripture, for the aboundance of all things
<pb facs="tcp:6744:10"/>neceſſary to the humane life; ſo the <hi>Dance</hi> is put in that Text for the greatnes of ioy. But let them marke, or remember one thing: The wordes muſt be vnderſtood in an other ſenſe, when they are repugnant vnto reaſon: but the word <hi>Dance,</hi> is not repugnant vnto reaſon, in that text of <hi>Ie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>remie</hi> aboue recited.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>To what eſtates the Dances are thought <hi>to be more becomming.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg>F wee will but marke meanely well a little part of the 15. Chap. of <hi>Exodus</hi> alreadie mentioned, it ſhall be ſufficiently manifeſt vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to vs, that the <hi>Iſraelitiſh</hi> women <hi>Danced</hi> with <hi>Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riam</hi> the Propheteſſe, for that they were moo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued and brought to it by the ſayd <hi>Miriam,</hi> which began to <hi>Dance,</hi> and was the leader of them. Whereby wee ſhall remaine fully perſwaded, that thoſe women did not embolden themſelues towardes that exerciſe, in the preſence of her, which was aboue them in dignitie, vntill they were bidden and inuited to it by her example.
<pb facs="tcp:6744:11"/>And this doth cauſe the opinions of many Lear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned men to be, that ſuch an exerciſe is rather ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pertayning to the Nobilitie and Gentilitie, then to the other eſtates: and that the inferiours ought not to vſe it among the ſuperiours, nor in the preſence of them, except the ſuperiours doe bidde or inuite the inferiours to the ſame, whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther it be by ſpeach, or otherwiſe. Concluding thereupon, that ſame Art to be much abuſed in our age, becauſe (ſay they) it is practiſed by a great many without any diſeretion at all.</p>
               <p>Let vs giue ſome inſight to a few words of the <hi>11.</hi> Chap. of <hi>Iudges,</hi> which wee haue alledged in another line of this Treatiſe. No mention is made of any perſon in thoſe Dances, but of the daughter of <hi>Iephtah,</hi> which was Captaine ouer the people of <hi>Iſrael,</hi> Doth not this argue with great probabilitie, that the ſaid daughter of <hi>Ieph<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tah,</hi> was the moouer and guider of that dancing, as ſhee was the higheſt in eſtate and condition among her fellowes? And doth it not by con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſequence come to agree with that purpoſe, which now we haue holden in a brief deduction, a very little before, about the dauncing of <hi>Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riam</hi> the Propheteſſe with the other women of <hi>Iſrael?</hi> None extraordinarie ſharpneſſe, or viua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>citie of wit is neceſſarie, to make it enter into
<pb facs="tcp:6744:11"/>the comprehenſion of that point.</p>
               <p>We haue already touched the fiftenth chap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter of the Booke of <hi>Iudeth,</hi> which wee muſt touch againe at this preſent time, vpon the diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>courſe which we haue in hand. For theſe words are written in the end of it, concerning the ſayde moſt honorable <hi>Iudeth, They alſo crowned her with Oliues, and her that was with her, and ſhee went before the people in the</hi> Dance, <hi>leading all the Women.</hi> Which words do greatly aug<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, without any part of doubt, the ſtrength and vigour of our argumentation: to wit, that the <hi>Dances</hi> do not ſeeme to become ſo well the lower ſort, as the higher: and that we may thinke according vnto reaſon, to be ſomewhat incon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uenient for the lower, to haue the exercitation of dancing neere the higher, vnleſſe ſome leaue he giuen of theſe vnto thoſe, one way or other. And herevnto this very ſhort addition, as we do perſwade our ſelues, cannot bee but fitly apply<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed: that by the Hiſtories of daunces contained in the holy Scripture, it ſeemeth vnto the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſideration of many godly perſons, that the pra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctiſe of <hi>Dancing</hi> is more becomming vnto wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men, then vnto men.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <pb facs="tcp:6744:12"/>
               <head>Why Dances are forbidden in ſome <hi>places among the Christians.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>He prohibition of <hi>Dan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces</hi> in <hi>Geneua,</hi> &amp; in ſome other Territories, which do keepe all the orders of the ſame in matters of Religion, and Eccleſiaſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>call Diſcipline, was made becauſe of the great abu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes of them: to cut off the pernicious euils, which oftentimes happened thereby. Is not this a ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficient argument, to prooue ſuch an action to be good? Behold, our <hi>Mesſias</hi> in the 18. Chap. of the Goſpel according to <hi>S. Matthew,</hi> doeth com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mand euery one of vs, to caſt away his hand, or his foote, or his eye; if they cauſe him to offend: ſaying, that it is better, to enter into life, with one hand, or with one foote, or with one eye, then hauing two hands, or two feete, or two eyes, to be caſt into euerlaſting fire. Therefore if in that caſe we muſt needs be depriued of things, which are ſo much profitable &amp; neceſſarie: why ſhould thoſe nations haue refuſed to ſuppreſſe a thing, which among them was become altogether
<pb facs="tcp:6744:12"/>vaine and prophane?</p>
               <p>Wee read in the <hi>21.</hi> Chap. of <hi>Numbers,</hi> that <hi>Moſes</hi> by the commandement of God, did make a Serpent of Braſſe, and erected it for a ſigne vnto the <hi>Iſraelites.</hi> And we read in the <hi>18.</hi> Chap. of the ſecond Booke of <hi>Kings,</hi> that the religious King <hi>Hezekiah</hi> did beat downe, and breake in peeces the ſayd Braſen Serpent, becauſe he ſaw that the people of <hi>Iſrael</hi> continued yet to adore the ſame, in burning Incenſe vnto it. If then it haue been lawfull, to aboliſh the Sacrament of God, in con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſideration that it was abuſed; why ſhould it not be lawfull, to put away the inuentions of men for the like cauſe?</p>
               <p>Mee thinketh it were enough, to make vs leaue and forſake the vſage of ſuch <hi>Dances,</hi> as are onely effected for the pleaſure of our eyes, to obſerue and conſider with ſtudious diligence one thing in the 14. chap. of the Apoſtle <hi>S. Matthew,</hi> How that through the meanes &amp; occaſion of a <hi>Dance, S. Iohn Baptiſt</hi> was put to death: which was a moſt excellent Prophet, &amp; a moſt faythfull fore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>runner of our Sauiour <hi>Ieſus Chriſt.</hi> To whom, with the <hi>Father,</hi> and the <hi>Spirit,</hi> be all magnifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cence, and glorie perpetually. <hi>Amen.</hi>
               </p>
               <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
            </div>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
